Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 10 -- Letters to Franklin, received during his residence in France ca.1776-1785 Mss.B.F85inventory10
American Philosophical Society
Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 10 -- Letters to Franklin, received during his residence in France
ca.1776-1785
Mss.B.F85inventory10
American Philosophical Society
1.0 section
This is part of the large inventory for the Benjamin Franklin Papers (Mss B F85). For complete information concerning this collection, please view the Collection Description.
273 items
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
- Letters received during Franklin's residence in France, ca.1776-1785
  - to Benjamin Franklin, August 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Aillaud, Madame
    Scope and Contents note
    Begging his influence with Comte de Buffon to procure her a pension; Mlle. Basseporte's precarious state of health renders this precaution necessary.
    (In French.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Appleton, John. Paris
    Accepting invitation to dine with Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, April 5; A.L.S. 3p.; Baberty, Jacques Christopher. Paris
    Asking for assistance to enable him to return to his family in Canada.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777? June 9]; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Bachelier, Jean Jacques
    Requests return of his memoir on "Le Cours d'Arts and Metiers."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L.S. 2p.; Baillard, Nicolas
    Was watchman of the ship "Eliza Belle" captured by American privateers; requests Franklin to let him have the wood used for packing the cargo of said vessel.
  - to William Temple Fracnklin, [1779 bet. March 21 and March 24]; A.L.S. 1p.; Bancroft, Edward
    Has received the enclosed letter (LXXIV, 97, see Vol. IV, p. 369) from Mrs. Bousie respecting the passport. Has some knowledge of Mr. Audibert, Captain of the Port of Calais, and from his letter has no doubt of Mr. Sartine's having given the passport mentioned.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Barisais, ----- de
    Application for assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Baussan, Madame N
    Very much annoyed that their trip to Versailles did not include more of Franklin's society; begs him to make it up to her another day.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Baussan, Madame N
    Postponing the date for a dinner to which Franklin was invited. Hopes Mme. Brillon and her family will be able to come with Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Berington, Joseph. Paris
    Presenting a letter of introduction from Dr. [Joseph] Priestley, with his last two publications; anxious to wait on Franklin at Passy, if his limited time permits. Urges Franklin to reunite a divided and falling empire.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Berna, -----
    Requesting Dr. Franklin to send his reply to a letter from M. Dumont of Mayence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, January 21; A.L.S. 2p.; de Bissey, Mlle. Paris
    Is a half orphan, aged eighteen; ill in bed at present; begs Franklin to come to see her; promises to excite his pity and deserves his assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 12p.; Blanchard, -----. Paris?
    Kindness shown him by M. de MacMahon. Detailed account of his present unfortunate situation; begs for assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 3p.; Blanchard, -----
    If Dr. Franklin cannot aid him in any material way, craves a few moments' audience.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Bond, D
    Asking a question or two concerning the certificates.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; de Bougon, -----
    Inquires what day he and Dr. Franklin are invited to dine at the Duc de la Val[l]ière's.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L.S. 1p.; Bourzeil, Dr de
    Sending a pamphlet on the science of healing.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Breda, Victor
    His present destitute condition; a Swiss by birth; taken prisoner by the English at the battle of Trenton; begs Franklin to send him back to America, where he desires to finish his days.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 2p.; Bremont, Alexis
    Served in the United States, begs Dr. Franklin for assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Dumay, Esther Brickland
    Appeal for assistance to enable her to rejoin her husband Ignace Dumay, who is at Metz.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 22d; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Was sorry to hear that Franklin has been ill. Will go to see him in a few days on her return to Passy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Saturday evening.; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Inviting Franklin to come to her house with a friend of his.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?] Tuesday 9th; A.L.S. 3p.; Brillon, Mme. Franconville
    Description of the country place where she is stopping. Would be happier living there always with her children and a few friends than in Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Wednesday morning.; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    M. [Francois Philippe] Charpentier, a skilful machinist and a friend of the Abbé de St. Non will call to see Franklin about some printing presses.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Dec. 10-15 Thursday morning; A.L.; Brillon, Mme
    Reminds Franklin of his promise to lend her one of his works in which he explains the phenomenon of water spouts. Likes serious and instructive reading.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Speaks of her sadness after Franklin's departure from her country house where he had stayed a few days. He has taken in her affections the place of her father whom she last too soon. Asks Franklin to come back again to her house with his son. [William Temple Franklin] and M. [Louis Guillaume] Le Veillard.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778 ?] Tuesday evening; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    "A band of corsairs," mostly of the female sex, is going to make an attack on Franklin's house and larder on Wednesday morning at 10 o'clock.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Thursday; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Her daughter being sick, is unable to call on Franklin that morning.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 30th Sunday; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    M. [Paul Jérémie] Bitaubé has been introduced to her. Asks Franklin to bring him on Wednesday evening. Does not think he needs to buy a certain secret for imitating handwriting, as he seems to have stolen it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778 ?] Sunday; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    M. Brillon has been unable to get a harp. Can send him a piano if it will serve his purpose.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February Thursday; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Relating an occurrence which had taken place at a friend's house when a certain American, and an intimate friend of Franklin, had insulted a lady there present by throwing her letter on the ground and walking on it. The lady is very angry over the affair. Only Franklin can arrange the matter. Invites him to tea and asks him to bring his compatriot.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, ----- Saturday; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Returning a letter of Franklin's for M. [Pierre Charles] de Parseval. Nothing to correct in it.
    Bibliography
    Printed in Proc. Am. Phil. Soc., XL, 110.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Wednesday morning.; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Sends a letter from the good Bishop of M---- who had just left for Corsica. Asks Franklin to carry out the Bishop's recommendations if possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Saturday; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Asks Franklin to return her the good Bishop's letter, as she wishes to write to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Chides Franklin for leaving her house earlier than usual one evening, because she was engaged with some ladies. Was annoyed and angry when she learned he had left so soon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?] Thursday morning.; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Does not know whether she can go to see Franklin that evening. Proposes to him to take tea at M. [Louis Guillaume] Le Veillard's on his return from Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778 before Nov. 30]; Tuesday 13th; A.L.S. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Asks Franklin to write to members of the French Academy whom he may know in favor of M. [Louis Guillaume] Le Veillard who is a candidate for one of the vacant seats. Sends him a list of the members entitled to vote.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, ----- Saturday.; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Asks him to come to her house at nine o'clock with his two sons.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781 February 8]; A Poem. 4p.; Brillon, Mme. Poem
    On the four seasons: Glycère (spring), Celimène (summer), Erigonne (autumn), and Cloris (winter). An allegorical tale in verse.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778? May]; A Ballad. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Colin and Lisette. Chanson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 July 30; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Sending a piece of music which she copied.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778 March 17]; A.N. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Sending an engraving presented to Franklin by Abbé de St. Non.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Wednesday; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Sends twelve engravings from the Abbé de St. Non for Franklin to give to his friends in Paris and America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Bruelt, R. Luxembourg
    Sending him a new treatise on Physics which he can recommend.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Burecourt, Chevalier de
    Eighty-five years old and bed-ridden; lacks the bare necessities of life; applies to Franklin for assistance.
    A. Mem. by Dr. Franklin. Doubts the truth of this story.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. in 3d P. 1p.; Pierre le Cacheur, Julien Bertols, ----- Farcis, and ----- Vincent
    Reasons for their arrest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L.S. 2p.; François Cadio and ----- Venant fils
    Request passports and passage to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Calkoen, -----
    A Dutch traveller who asks for an interview with "the Patron of Liberty."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. 1p.; A Charitable Committee for the Assistance of Prisoners
    Soliciting Franklin's aid.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. 1p.; Chemisard, Guillaume
    Requesting an interview.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Clauser, -----. Paris
    Sending Franklin an engraving or printing machine, entrusted to his care by M. de Goué.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Comte, Jacques
    Ship captain of Bordeaux wishes to confer with Franklin on some American business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, May 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Constard, Mme. Paris
    Forwarding a letter to Franklin on behalf of one of her friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; de Covay, Mme
    Recommends a cook to Dr. Franklin in case he needs one.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Croize, Pierre
    Begging Franklin to render them some assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. 2p.; Andrieu, ------ d'
    Petitions for assistance to enable him to go to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Defouchy, ------
    Has received no reply to his former request for a moment's audience; desires to speak with him on an important matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Defouchy, Mr., Mme. and Mlle.
    Called to see Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; De Lome, John Louis
    Called to see him before leaving for England but finding him occupied did not care to interrupt him, will call again.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [c 1779 May 11]; A.L.S. 2p.; Crenis, Chevalier de
    Owing to illness is obliged to forward Franklin the letters entrusted to him by Mr. and Mrs. [Richard] Bache.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Des Etres, -----. Paris
    Asking for a few moments' audience.
    A. E. by Franklin. Mentioning the day and hour.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Desmarain, -----
    Presenting Franklin with a basket of strawberries, the fruits of his own gardening.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 6p.; Devellenne, -----. Paris
    Statement in Bacon's Philosophical Works that the Greeks condemned to death the first physicists who presumed to explain the natural causes of thunder; applies to Franklin for aid in verifying this. Question of a belief in God; attitude of Voltaire—of Socrates.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 3p.; Deville, Mme
    Confined to her bed by an illness lasting six months; in great need of money; offers to sell Franklin a rare old trinket for four louis.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?]; A.L.S. 1p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, -----
    Recommending M. Prevost a man of much talent who desires to have an interview with him before going to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?] March 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, -----
    Requesting Dr. Franklin to allow M. Gardeur to paint his portrait.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, December 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Dupaty, Charles Marguerite Jean Baptiste Mercier. Paris
    Criticism of the book lent him by Franklin; begs for the loan of the other volumes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Dursousquet, -----
    Begging Franklin's charity on behalf of his two children, both in the cradle and without bread to eat.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Dursousquet, -----
    Asking for succor for himself and his two children, abandoned by their mother.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1776 Dec. 30 - 1777 Feb. 26]; N. in 3d P. 1p.; An English Gentleman
    Wishes an interview.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; d'Etioles, Lenormant
    Regrets having missed Franklin when he called with M. Bougon; authorized by the Comte de Vergennes to speak with Franklin on an important matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 28 Thursday; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Filleul, Mme
    Requests Dr. Franklin to send her word about the Comtesse d'Artois, if he has received any news that day.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Wednesday; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Filleul, Mme
    Sends the three last volumes of the Memoirs of Baron Delott. Request Dr. Franklin to send her the day's journal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780] [June] 13; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Filleul, Louis
    Announcing the birth of a son.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Filleul, Mme
    Requesting Franklin to take her in his carriage to the ball at Mme. Brillion's.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Fox, John
    A begging letter from one who suffered in America's struggle for freedom.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Fox, John
    An Englishman by birth but married and settled in France, is in distress and appeals to Franklin for assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 4p.; Frederic, F
    A French priest; desires Franklin's influence with the King to procure him the place of Chaplain; number of savages he converted to the Roman Catholic religion, at the same time making them faithful subjects of France and America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. 1p.; A French Sailor
    Appeal for assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?]; L.S. 1p.; Froncy, Jean Jacques
    Is condemned to imprisonment for life for the larceny of a small sum of money; begs Franklin to use his influence to obtain his release.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779 C. March]; A.L.S. 2p.; Froncy, Jean Jacques. Brest
    Asking him to procure his release from prison.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Gautier, -----. Paris
    Presenting Franklin with a ring of his own workmanship, a sardonyx with an engraved allegorical design.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 2p.; Gautier, Jacques
    Is a poor sailor; begs for assistance to go to Bordeaux.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L.S. 1p.; Gerard, -----
    Is a writer and man of letters. Forced by necessity and want to discontinue a literary work he was engaged on. Appeals to Franklin for help to enable him to continue his writings.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Gerard, -----
    Brusque and cruel refusal of his request for assistance; driven to importune him by his necessities.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780?]; Mem. 1p.; Gonnet, Antoine
    Concerning a protested note.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Gouther, Jean David
    Begging for aid to enable him to return to his native place in Switzerland.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Granchez, D.P
    Requests Dr. Franklin to return a compass which was delivered in mistake for his own.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Sending Franklin his reply to M. [Jean] Durival, which if approved, can be sent at once by M. de Vergennes's courier.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778?; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Sending him the new proof; asks for his opinion in order that he may give the printer his instructions.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780? Nov. 29]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    No reply received from Versailles concerning the letter for Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780 Dec. 18]; A.L. 3p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Relating to the bills M. [Le Ray] de Chaumont had obtained from him for the freight.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [on or After 1780 December 21]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Sending paper for Frankin to sign, also the two bills of M. [Le Ray] de Chaumont.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780]; A.L. 2p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Case of an American, M. Myers, who had his trunk containing bills on Congress and valuable papers, stolen from his carriage; fears it was the work of a spy and not a thief.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Thinks it necessary to go to Versailles. If Franklin can lend him his carriage would leave early in the morning.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    With reference to an error of figures in the amount of a draft presented for payment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Requesting Franklin to sign a draft.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777 ?]; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Requesting Franklin to look over the draft of a memoir which he is drawing up for him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, on or After May 11; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    He and M. Boux have arrived from Paris and wish to see Messrs. Franklin and [William] Carmichael.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [before Dec. 10]; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    With reference to Comte de Vergennes and to a claim which he (Grand) had to certain moneys.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Saturday morning.; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, The Family
    Asking if Dr. Franklin will do them the honor to dine with them on Sunday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Grand, ------ l'ainé
    Expressing his father's regret at not seeing Franklin, owing to illness. Acknowledging Franklin's interest in the birth of his child.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Grand, Madame Ferdinand
    Has commenced the coverlet in order to make the work easier for his daughter [Mrs. Richard Bache]; sends it together with the ivory needles. Condoles with him on the inconstancy of one of his loves, who is to marry M. de Forbouay.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, Sir George
    Date of the Abbé de Breteuil's dinner. M. Boux's affair.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, Henry
    Sending Franklin particulars of the failure of the firm of Marlar and Stewart in London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, Henry
    Returning his order relative to Mr. [John] Jay's acceptances. Asking his approbation to the list of bills sent by Messrs. Parish and Thomson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779 May or After]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, Henry
    Desiring a passport for an English lady.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, (1778) November 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Grand, Henry. Paris
    Introducing Mr. Henry Jarley who is eager for an interview with Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Before April 23; A.L. in 3d. P. 1p.; Grand, Henry
    At his father's request sends Franklin the enclosed letter. Desires to know Franklin's determination relative to his account.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Grand, Henry
    Desiring Benjamin Franklin's presence at his house to see the Procession du Bon Dieu.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Greuze, Mme
    Asks Franklin to use his good offices in favor of a French officer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 21; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Guicherit, -----
    Forwarding a letter to Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Guilin, -----
    A fruit dealer at Chaillot; complains of being deprived of his custom through the ill will of Franklin's butler.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Guyot, -----
    Will set out for England on Tuesday. Called to take leave of Dr. Franklin and receive his orders.
  - to Benjamin Franklin and the Marquis de Lafayette., [1779 After March 3]; Verses S. 1p.; Halliman, John. Marquis
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 3p.; d'Halluin, Madame
    Lives by the work of her hands; sends Franklin two vests which she begs him to purchase for four and a half louis.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, May 30; A.L.S. 1p.; d'Halluin, Madame
    Acknowledging the important service rendered her by Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, August 8; A.L.S. 3p.; d'Halluin, Madame
    Forced to quit France on business; lacks the means for travelling; begs Franklin to buy the enclosed book for three louis.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Haltzendorff, Baronne d'
    Requesting him to forward a letter for her.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Hardoncelle, Mme d'
    Asks him to induce M. [Le Ray] de Chaumont to accept an invitation to dine with her.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. ind 3d P. 2p.; Hardoncelle, Mme d'
    Will call on Franklin the next Monday and take breakfast with him. Invites him to go afterwards to Surennes with some friends and dine.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 4p.; Havet, ------. Montreuil
    Begging Franklin's assistance on behalf of a widow and two young children in his parish.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Hooper, I
    His decision to return to America; begs Franklin to assist him in procuring convenient accommodations on a ship bound for the Continent.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Hooper, I. Paris
    Sets out early in the morning for Orléans; if he should hear of any other than the present opportunity, begs to be notified.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Jamogne, Mme de
    Desiring his opinion of the reply made by her relative, M. le Chevalier de la Haullde [?] to the proposition of M. de Loyauté for a regiment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A. Verses, S. 1p.; Jarry, —, abbé
    Lines in eulogy of Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Jaucourt, Count de
    Requests Franklin to appoint a time when he can confer with him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Thursday noon; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Jones, Dr
    Accepting his invitation to dinner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Joyce, Miss
    Sending a letter to Dr. Franklin which she has received from Lisbon with Mr. and Mrs. D'arcy's compliments.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. 1p.; Réau de-Keranguez, Chevalier de
    His rank and address at Versailles.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Kiddell, John Jr. Paris
    Having made a tour through Spain, is returning to England, via France; desires to pay his respects and offer his services to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Kossakowski, Abbé Corvini
    Accepting Dr. Franklin's invitation of dinner for himself and Abbé Strzozki, astronomer of the King of Poland.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Lahannée, Louise
    Is a pastry cook; complains she has lost Franklin's custom through the ill-will of his butler and begs Franklin to renew it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Landells, John
    Is a native of Philadelphia, petitions for assistance to enable him to return to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779 before June 19]; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Innocent Hector de Maillart, Comte de Landreuville
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; La Rochefoucauld, Louis Alexandre, duc de
    Is obliged to go to Versailles on Sunday but hopes to be free early enough to avail himself of Franklin's invitation to dinner.